<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons preached in the Tovver. The former, on Sunday the 30. day of Ianuary. 1641. The later, on Sunday the 24. day of April. 1642. By the Bishop of Bath and Wells.</title>
            <author>Piers, William, 1580-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E155_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23322</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871971</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871971</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156862</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90696)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156862)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E155[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons preached in the Tovver. The former, on Sunday the 30. day of Ianuary. 1641. The later, on Sunday the 24. day of April. 1642. By the Bishop of Bath and Wells.</title>
                  <author>Piers, William, 1580-1670.</author>
                  <author>W. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.H. for Charles Greene, and are to be sold in Ivy Lane at the signe of the Gun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XLII. [1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Bishop of Bath and Wells = William Piers.</note>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed by the editor, W.D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156862:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS Preached In the Tovver.</p>
            <p>The former, On Sunday the 30. day of Ianury. 1641.</p>
            <p>The later, On Sunday the 24. day of April. 1642.</p>
            <p>By <hi>The Biſhop of Bath and Wells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. H.</hi> for <hi>Charles Greene,</hi> and are to be ſold in Ivy Lane at the ſigne of the Gun. MDCXLII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:156862:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156862:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I have ſeene a Sermon in print, under the name of the Biſhop of Bath and Wells, (but without his Lordſhips conſent or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge I am ſure) whereat I was an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive auditor, and I finde many groſſe errors in that Impreſsion; for therein many ſentences are imperfect, many words are miſplaced, many paſſages are omitted, and the ſenſe in many things is utterly miſtaken: whereby the Biſhop ſuffereth in his credit, and the Reader is abuſed in his expectation. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I doe beleeve he that tooke the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in writing when it was preacht, had no intention at all, by printing it,
<pb facs="tcp:156862:3"/>to wrong the Authour. Therefore I thought fit, for the Churches good, and to do the Biſhop right, to publiſh (though much againſt his Lordſhips minde) a true and entire copie of that firſt, and alſo of this other Sermon preached ſince by him in the ſame place, for which I ſtayed untill now, otherwiſe I had play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Midwife with the former long ſince; but now the worke is complete, and I wiſh thee as much comfort and benefit in reading both theſe Sermons, as I had in hearing them. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W.D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:156862:3"/>
            <head>The firſt SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>The Text. 2 COR. 12.8, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>For this thing I beſought the Lord thrice that it might depart from me. And hee ſaid unto mee, My grace is ſufficient for thee, for my ſtrength is made perfect in weakneſſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hich words have dependance upon the Verſe next before, wherein St. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us, that leſt he ſhould have beene exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove meaſure through abundance of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, there was given unto him a thorne in the fleſh, the meſſenger of Satan to buffet him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:156862:4"/>Now for this thing, what thing? Why this thorn in the fleſh which did grieve him, this meſſenger of Satan which did buffet him, he beſought the Lord thrice that it might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from him.</p>
            <p>So then the cauſe of his earneſt prayer was the thorne in his fleſh, the Meſſenger of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; and the occaſion of that thorne in his fleſh, that meſſenger of Satan, was the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Viſions and Revelations from the Lord: no Apoſtle had ſo many, none ſo great.</p>
            <p>But the greater the favour of God was to him herein, the greater was his danger of falling into ſpiritual pride, &amp; ſuperexaltation of himſelf; the moſt dangerous ſin that the child of God can fal into Indeed Gods grace &amp; our humbleneſſe of minde ſhould go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and the greater the graces are which wee receive from God, the more humble muſt wee bee in our ſelves; and me more humbly ought we to walke with our God This is the coherence of the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:156862:4"/>The parts in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall are two.
<list>
                  <item>The firſt is St. <hi>Pauls</hi> petition un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, in the former verſe, <hi>For this, thing I beſought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The ſecond is Gods anſwer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>And he ſaid unto me, My grace is ſufficient for thee; for my ſtrength is made perfect in weakneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition conſiſts of theſe five branches
<list>
                  <item>1. The firſt was the cauſe of his complaint, <hi>non calceus urget,</hi> it was not his ſhooe that did wring him, no ſmal matter that did trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him, but ſomething that went to his very heart, whatſoever it was; <hi>propter quod, for this thing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The ſecond was the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or meanes that he uſed againſt this thing that did ſo trouble him, and that was prayer, <hi>Propter quod rogavi, for this thing I beſought.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The third was the earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or importunity of his prayer, he gave not over untill he had an
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156862:5"/>anſwer, <hi>propter quod rogaviter, for this thing I prayed thrice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. The fourth was the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian upon whom he called to help him, and that was God himſelfe, no other could doe it, <hi>propter quod ter rogavi Dominum, for this thing I beſought the Lord thrice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. The laſt was the end of his petition, the thing that he did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and that was that he might be freed from that which did ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict him, <hi>propter quod rogavi Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ter ut diſcederet à me, for this thing I beſought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:156862:5"/>In the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer I obſerve theſe 3. particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt the effect of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, it was a denyall, hee prayed that the thorne which ſtucke ſo faſt in his fleſh might bee pluckt out, that the meſſenger of Satan which buffeted him, might depart from him; but it would not bee; he muſt bee content to endure it: and this appeares upon the whole anſwer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Gods divine ayd againſt the thing that did ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Apoſtle, to make him able to encounter the ſame, and in the end to maſter it.</p>
            <p>Wherein we have both the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this ayd, what kinde of ayd it was, it was his grace, <hi>gratia mea, my grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo the meaſure and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy thereof, there was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of it, and it was po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull, <hi>ſufficit tibi, it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee then God denyed the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle that thing which he prayed for, but he gave him another, and a better thing which hee did not pray for, and that was his grace.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The reaſon both of Gods denyall, to remove that which troubled him; and alſo of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ayd againſt the thing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156862:6"/>he did complaine, expreſſed by God himſelfe in a maxime, or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſentence in Divinity; which reaſon is drawne from Gods courſe or way which hee takes with his ſervants in his wiſdome, and in his mercy, both for his owne glory, and mans eternall good. <hi>Nam virtus mea in infirmita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te perficitur,</hi> for my ſtrength is made perfect in weakneſſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the ſeverall parts and Branches of the Text, and of all theſe in their order, And firſt of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Petition to God, and therein I begin with the cauſe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, <hi>propter quod, for this thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What this thing was in generall that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled this Apoſtle, he tells us in the verſe next before my Text, wherein hee deſcribes it two wayes: Firſt, by a metaphor or figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative phraſe, in reſpect of the paine and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it cauſed, calling it <hi>ſtimulum in carne,</hi> a thorne in his fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:156862:6"/>The word in Greeke is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a ſmall ſharp goad, or prick, againſt many whereof Saint <hi>Paul</hi> kickt before his converſion, <hi>Acts</hi> the ninth, <hi>ver.</hi> five, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls <hi>ſudem,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>palum praeacutum,</hi> a ſharpe ſtake or point of a ſpeare, <hi>vel aliquid acuminatum,</hi> or any thing that hath a long ſhar pe end, which ſticking in a mans body, cauſeth an intollerable paine.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he deſcribes it plainely in reſpect of the Author, framer or contriver of it, and ſo hee calls it <hi>Angelum Satanae,</hi> the Meſſenger of Satan, which did buffet him, for God permitted Satan ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>Now two things are certaine here; one, that it was Satans vexation by Gods permiſſion; the other, that it did daily afflict him to the very heart.</p>
            <p>So then you ſee it was no briar, no prickle, no nor no thorne, no ſmall thing, that ſo troubled the Apoſtle, but a great matter indeed; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Engliſh tranſlations call it a thorne in in the fleſh; and becauſe we have not a better word in Engliſh to expreſſe it, I will call it ſtill by that name.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:156862:7"/>But now what this thing, this thorne in the fleſh was in particular, thats all the doubt indeed, and this is—<hi>dignus vindice nodus.</hi> And here I muſt confeſſe I am fallen among thornes, even the various opinions of Divines concerning this thing, which pluck me this way and that way, ſo that I can ſconer finde an entrance in, then a paſſage out.</p>
            <p>Some Divines draw this thorne in the fleſh, of which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> complaines, as farre as from <hi>Adams</hi> loynes, and ſay it was originall concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, which the Apoſtle calls <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gem in carne,</hi> a law in his fleſh, in his members, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>But this conceit is too farre fetcht; for firſt, Originall ſinne is generall to all the Regenerate; but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> complaines here of ſome ſpeciall thing which happened only to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Againe, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> knew very well that Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne could not poſſibly depart from him, as long as he lived in this world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. but hee prayed earneſtly that this thing might depart from him.</p>
            <p>Other Divines, with moſt of the Latine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, affirme, that this thing which ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the Apoſtle was ſome ſore diſeaſe or infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156862:7"/>of his body, as a continuall head ach, or paine in his ſtomacke, or the gout, or the ſtone, or ſome ſuch griefe which daily afflicted him.</p>
            <p>But this is not likely, for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth not complaine in any of his Epiſtles of any diſeaſe or infirmity of his body beſides this; ſuch a mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy would have beene a great impediment to him in the preaching of Gods word, &amp; planting of the Goſpell of Chriſt in all Countries, which hee could never have done, if he had been continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tormented with any ſuch infirmity of the body.</p>
            <p>The Greeke Fathers, with many moderne Writers affirme, that this thing, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> praied might depart from him, was his adverſaries in generall, as <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> whom Satan ſtirred up againſt him with contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melies and perſecutions to hinder the preaching of the Goſpel; but eſpecially and particularly that peſtilent adverſary of his <hi>Alexander</hi> the Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſmith, who did him much evill, and of whom he complaines, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. and he bids <hi>Tumothy</hi> to beware of him alſo; for ſaith the Apoſtle, Hee hath greatly withſtood our words.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, this <hi>Alexander</hi> was one of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156862:8"/>meſſengers, and his reproaches were Satans buffettings, but he and the reſt of the adverſaries of the Goſpel, were <hi>Thornes</hi> without his fleſh, but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> complaines here of ſome <hi>Thorne</hi> in his fleſh, ſome internall affliction that came cloſer to him.</p>
            <p>But other Divines are of opinion that God did permit ſome evill Angell of Satan to vex and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the body of this bleſſed Apoſtle, as he did permit Satan to vex and torment the body of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Iob,</hi> and that this Angell of Satan did buffet St. <hi>Paul</hi> as one man would buffer another, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed many a blacke and blue marke upon him.</p>
            <p>Like as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> was paid with many a ſore blow in an exſtaſie, for reading <hi>Cicero</hi> more then the <hi>Bible,</hi> when he heard a voice ſaying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>Ciceronianus es, non Chriſtianus,</hi> thou art a Ciceronian, thou art no Chriſtian, as Saint <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> reporteth of himſelfe in an Epiſtle to <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtochius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, although this ſeeme to be the plain literall ſenſe of the words, yet I cannot beleeve that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was thus bodily afflicted with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny evill ſpirit by fits, for then he would never
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156862:8"/>have called it <hi>ſtimulum in carne,</hi> a thorne ſo deeply faſtned in his fleſh; beſides, if it had beene ſo, the moſt heroicall Spirit of this Apoſtle, which was ſo far above all the buffettings of Men and Divels, would not have complained of ſuch a thing, but rather have gloried in it.</p>
            <p>All the Romaniſts both old and new are not aſhamed to affirme that this <hi>thing</hi> which ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the Apoſtle, was <hi>Stimulus libidinis,</hi> a tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and provocation of carnall luſt, which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ſtirred up in the fleſh, and in his fancy, by ſuch meanes as he knew very well would doe it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which he did keep his body under, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9 for if it had beene any thing elſe but this, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would have told us plainly what it had beene; but now it being a thing whereof hee was aſhamed, he covered it modeſtly under the metaphor of a <hi>Thorne</hi> in his fleſh. So <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his 2. Booke <hi>de Monachis, cap</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Eraſmus</hi> rightly cals this <hi>impurum inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretamentum,</hi> an impure interpretation, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that any learned and honeſt Divine ſhould goe about to caſt ſuch filth upon the face of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> then aged, and very much broken with the labours of his Miniſtery, and to entertaine
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156862:9"/>ſo unworthy a conceit of ſo chaſte and holy an Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Againe, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had the gift of chaſtity; I would to God all men were as I my ſelfe am, but every man hath his proper gift of God, one after this manner, and another after that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. where was then this urging luſt?</p>
            <p>But if the Apoſtle here had beene troubled with any ſuch temptation, he knew a very eaſie and an honeſt remedy againſt it, even the ſame which he gave to others in the like caſe, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we ſay then? what <hi>thing</hi> was this that did ſo trouble him? Why certainly in the judgement of the moſt orthodox Divines, who goe to the very roote of my Text, it was ſome terior of Satan, ſome internall and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all temptation in his ſoule, and a very ſore one whatſoever it was.</p>
            <p>And when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith it was <hi>in carne,</hi> in his fleſh, he means in the outward man, in the unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>te part of the ſoule, as in the ſeventh to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:156862:9"/>Although a continuall temptation or afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the conſcience, may alſo be ſaid to be in the fleſh, <hi>per modum redundantia &amp; participationis,</hi> by way of participation and redundancy, becauſe the fleſh in ſuch a caſe becomes pale and wan, and pines away.</p>
            <p>The beſt conjecture of all is this, that God did permit Satan to preſent alwaies before the conſcience of this Apoſtle his former blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, perſecutions and cruelties againſt Chriſt and his Church, and to ring alwaies in his eares that voice, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gods purpoſe herein being to keepe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> from ſpirituall pride with which he might eaſily have ſwolne through the abundance of Revelations of the Lord; but Satans pollicy herein was to weaken and ſhake the Apoſtles confidence in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>thorne</hi> is hid ſo deep in the fleſh that I will ſearch after it no further, but content my ſelf with Saint <hi>Auſtines docta ignorantia,</hi> learned igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in this, who ingeniouſly confeſſeth that he knew not particularly what this <hi>thing</hi> was which ſo troubled this Apoſtle, but ſure he was,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156862:10"/>it was ſome ſore temptation or other affliction; and in this all Divines agree.</p>
            <p>You ſee then here, that an Apoſtle, and ſuch an Apoſtle as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was, and after ſo many Viſions and Revelations of the Lord, had a thorne in the fleſh given him, a ſore affliction from God; and no marvell, for the better the man, the ſharper and the deeper the <hi>thorne:</hi> it muſt be ſo.</p>
            <p>As the Church of God in generall, ſo every childe of God in his Church, is <hi>ſicut lilium inter ſpinas,</hi> as a lilly among thornes 2. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. the thornes of troubles and afflictions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non decet ſub ſpinoſo capite membrum eſſe delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> he is not worthy to be a member of the myſticall body of Chriſt, upon whoſe glorious head was platted a crowne of many thornes for the ſinnes of other men, who cannot endure the pricking of one <hi>thorne,</hi> ſome light affliction, if not for his Saviours ſake, yet for his owne ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Hath our bleſſed Saviour dranke ſo deepe of the cup of afflictions before us, and for us, and ſhall we be unwilling to pledge him a little, to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156862:10"/>ſip after him in the ſame cup? <hi>Qui erat ſine flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, non erat ſine flagello.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since God ſpared not his owne and onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne who was without all ſpot of ſin, but delivered him up for us all, ſhall wee who are but his adopted ſonnes, and altogether ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, thinke to eſcape without any chaſtiſement at all? No, no, the Lord chaſteneth every Son whom he receiveth, and therefore <hi>qui non eſt in numero flagellatorum, non eſt in numero filiorum,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> He that is without chaſtiſement is a baſtard, and not a ſon, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.8.</p>
            <p>Give me the man, ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that was never troubled with any thorne of temptation or affliction, and I will preſently conclude, that that man is not the child of God; for every childe of God muſt have ſomething, one affliction or other to humble him, and to bring him home to God, in which he muſt take pleaſure, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did.</p>
            <p>We muſt not thinke to goe <hi>à deliciis ad delicias,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Ierom,</hi> immediately from the pleaſures of this world, to the joyes of the next: The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael went not through gardens of flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, and Paradiſes of fruits, but through un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156862:11"/>deſerts to the land of <hi>Candan;</hi> this was a type of our pilgrimage through the afflictions of this world to the heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Afflictions are the infallible arguments and to kens of Gods favour unto us; and therefore one who had beene a great while without any affliction, ſaid in his Prayer to God, <hi>ergóne Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne non ſun dignus qui patiar,</hi> is it ſo Lord, and I ſo much out of thy favour that I am not worthy of affliction?</p>
            <p>What a large Catalogue doth St. <hi>Paul</hi> reckon up of his afflictions in the eleventh Chapter of this Epiſtle, <hi>In ſtripes above meaſure, in priſons more frequent, in deaths oft: Of the Iewes five times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived I forty ſtripes ſave one, thrice was I beaten with rods, once was I ſtoned, thrice I ſuffered ſhipwracke, a night and a day have I beene in the deepe; in journying often, in perills of waters, in perills of robbers, in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rills by mine owne Countrimen, in perills by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, in perills in the City, in perills in the wilderneſſe, in perills in the ſea, in perills among falſe brethren, in wearineſſe and painfulneſſe, in watchings often, in hunger and thirſt, in faſtings often, in cold and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> I am almoſt out of breath in rehearſing them, and yet the Apoſtle was never out of breath in enduring them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:156862:11"/>But here was his comfort, and here is ours alſo: All the afflictions of the ſervants of God, they are but <hi>ſtimuli,</hi> the prickings of thornes, they are but <hi>colaphi</hi> the buffettings cauſing ſhame and ſmart onely, they are but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the gentle pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſnments of a loving father: <hi>We are troubled, but not altogether diſtreſſed, perplexed, but not in deſpaire, perſecuted, but not forſaken, caſt downe but not deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8.9.</p>
            <p>O welcome then, yea thrice welcome to our ſoules theſe bitter ſweets, loving chaſtiſements, gentle corrections, indulgent viſitations, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant croſſes, comfortable ſorrowes, wholeſome calamities, profitable miſeries, ſanctifying diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, refining troubles, joyfull temptations, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous trialls, bleſſed revilings, happy curſes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable reproaches, all light and momentary afflictions, which worke for us a farre more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and eternall weight of glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>By theſe we are humbled, and ſeeke right early unto our God.</p>
            <p>By theſe we are put in remembrance to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for our ſinnea paſt.</p>
            <p>By theſe wee become more carefull of our waies hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:156862:12"/>By theſe Gods graces are exerciſed in us, and our patience, our faith and our love are tried.</p>
            <p>By theſe wee are weaned from the pleaſures and vanities of this life.</p>
            <p>By theſe wee are prepared and fitted for the world to come.</p>
            <p>By theſe our deſires are inflamed to be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and to be with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>By theſe we are encouraged to embrace death with both our armes: and therefore <hi>David</hi> ſaid unto God, I know that of very faithfulneſſe, that is in thy faithfull love to methou haſt cauſed me to be troubled, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. verſe 75.</p>
            <p>I have been the longer upon this firſt branch, the thing which troubled the Apoſtle, becauſe it is the thing upon which the whole frame of my Text doth turne, I will therefore be the ſhorter in the reſt.</p>
            <p>But what did the Apoſtle here when the <hi>thorne</hi> of affliction began to vex him? Why, he went preſently to his prayers, the onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or ſoveraigne medicine to draw out the <hi>thorne</hi> of any temptation or affliction what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. For <hi>this thing</hi> rogavi <hi>I beſought,</hi> which is the ſecond branch of the petition, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156862:12"/>comes in the next place to bee handled.</p>
            <p>Is any man afflicted, let him pray, this was St. <hi>Iames</hi> his precept in the fifth Chapter of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, verſe 13. and this was <hi>Davids</hi> practice, In my diſtreſſe I called upon the Lord, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained unto my God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. yea God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaies, wee will be ſure to pray unto him when we are in trouble, whatſoever wee doe at other times; For in their affliction they will ſeek me early, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15.</p>
            <p>We uſe to make prayer the laſt remedy and refuge onely in our extremities, when all other meanes faile, then to our prayers, but it ought to be the firſt too, for God is a very preſent helpe in trouble, ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 46.1. other helpes are not alwaies at hand, but Gods helpe is.</p>
            <p>But will not God helpe us without our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? No, and why ſo? Firſt, becauſe prayer is a part of the worſhip and ſervice of God, which we owe unto him: The great men of the world will not beſtow their favours, nor grant delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances untill they bee petitioned, and ſhall the great God of heaven and earth beſtow his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and ſhew his mercy upon us without our praiers? Secondly, becauſe our praiers ſhew our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156862:13"/>confidence in Gods power and providence, in his mercy and love: A father can give his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſon all that he wants without his praiers, but he will not, becauſe he delights to have him ſue to him.</p>
            <p>Yea but Gods decrees are immutable, and his will is unchangeable, how then can our praiers incline him this way or that way? Thus indeed have wicked wits reaſoned againſt praier; but it is a true and a well known rule, <hi>ſubordinata non pugnant inter ſe,</hi> things which are ſubordinate are not contrary one to the other; and ſuch are Gods decrees and our prayers, as God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the end, ſo hath he ordained the meanes; now Gods purpoſes are not hindred by our praiers, but rather executed, and our praiers are as it were the midwives to deliver them, and the ſecond cauſes and meanes to effect his decrees; Chriſt knew that all thoſe things which hee prayed for would be granted before he prayed; but yet he prayed for them.</p>
            <p>But now as our prayers in affliction muſt be fervent, ſo muſt they bee frequent too, and therefore the Apoſtle prayed often, <hi>ter,</hi> thrice,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156862:13"/>that this <hi>thing, this affliction might depart from him;</hi> which is the third branch of this Petition.</p>
            <p>A medicine muſt be often applied, otherwiſe it will not worke the cure; here is a certaine number for an uncertaine, thrice for often, as <hi>ter beatus,</hi> thrice happy, is very happy, ſo when the Apoſtle ſaid here, <hi>ter rogavi,</hi> I prayed thrice, he meanes often, or very much, importunately, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven untill the Lord anſwered him.</p>
            <p>Is thy praier denied the firſt and the ſecond time? why then, it is very likely thou haſt made ſome fault in thy prayer: Yee aske and receive not, becauſe ye aske amiſſe, ſaith St. <hi>Iames, Iames</hi> 4.3. go to it therefore the third time, and by often praying thou ſhalt finde out the error of thy prayer.</p>
            <p>If God heare thee not in thine affliction at the firſt and ſecond knocke, it is to prove thy pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, thy faith and thy love: <hi>Oſtium Coeli forſitan proptere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> clauſum eſt ut ta fortiùs pulſes,</hi> Heaven gate is therefore perhaps ſhut that thou maiſt knocke the longer and the lowder, give not over knocking then untill the doore be opened.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:156862:14"/>
               <hi>Magna beneficia magnis precibus ſunt comparanda,</hi> great bleſſings are not to bee obtained but with importunate prayers.</p>
            <p>Did the unrighteous Judge in the Goſpell yeeld at laſt to the importunate prayer of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow? And ſhall not the righteous Judge of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, thinke ye, yeeld to the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate prayers of his owne deare ſervants in their afflictions?</p>
            <p>The Kingdome of Heaven ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it by force: what force? Why the force of prayer, <hi>&amp; haec vis Deo grata,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and this violence is moſt pleaſing unto Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincunt invincibilem ligant omnipotentem,</hi> our frequent and importunate prayers overcame him that is invincible, and binde him who is omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent.</p>
            <p>But if our love and obedience to God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not excite us to this frequency of prayer, yet I am ſure the <hi>thorne</hi> of affliction will urge us to call often upon the Lord, who is our onely refuge in time of trouble, <hi>rogavi Dominum, I prayed unto the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> which is the firſt branch of this Petition.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:156862:14"/>We have neither precept nor practice in all the canonicall Scriptures for praying to any other in heaven but onely unto the Lord. Whom have I in heaven but thee, ſaid <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 73.25. but the Papiſts are not of <hi>Davids</hi> Religion in this point, for they have their St. <hi>Franc is</hi> and St. <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> and thouſands more in heaven, whom they pray unto beſides the Lord, nay they have almoſt for every ſeverall kinde of evill a ſeverall Saint; they pray unto their Saint <hi>Apollonia</hi> againſt the toothach, to their Saint <hi>Petronella</hi> againſt a fever, to their Saint <hi>Roch</hi> againſt the plague, to their Saint <hi>Liberius</hi> againſt the ſtone, to their Saint <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> againſt a tempeſt at ſea, to their St. <hi>Leonard</hi> againſt bonds and impriſonment, and to other Saints againſt the like evills, as <hi>Cornelius a lapide,</hi> one of their owne writers, is not aſhamed to confeſſe in his Commentaries upon the ſecond Chapter of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the Hebrewes. He muſt bee a good Arithmetician that can rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon up the names of all their Saints, upon whom they cal when they are in any trouble or danger, thus they diſhonour God, and rob him of his worſhip by their ſuperſtitious invocation of Saints departed, who cannot hear nor help them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:156862:15"/>That ſame cantlike argument of the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, that we muſt not, or we ſhould not preſume to goe immediately to a King with our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but we muſt firſt make our way by a Maſter of Requeſts or by a favourite, doth not deſerve a ſcholarlike anſwer; for God is is every where, and his ears are open to our prayers, and he knoweth the thoughts of our hearts long before they are thought, and hee hath no other Maſter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, but the Spirit it ſelfe to make interceſſion for us, no other favourite to preſent out praiers but his deare Son and our bleſſed Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who is our Advocate at the right hand of God. And ſo I come to the end of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Petition, which was, that the thing which did ſo trouble him might goe away from him, <hi>Vt diſcederet à me,</hi> that it might depart from me.</p>
            <p>Afflictions in themſelves are unpleaſing and contrary to our nature; and therefore in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not to be wiſhed for or deſired, but to bee borne with patience, comfortand joy, when God ſends them, as being profitable for us.</p>
            <p>As medicines in phyſicke which are made of corrected poyſons are very good for us, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156862:15"/>therefore we are willing to take them, but wee would not have them ſtay with us, but when they have done their worke, we would have them depart from us, it is even ſo with our afflictions.</p>
            <p>But in the meane time, although theſe <hi>thornes</hi> of affliction be not preſently pluckt out, theſe meſſengers of Satan doe not ſtraight way depart from us, yet they ſhall never make us deſpaire of Gods goodneſſe and mercy, neither ſhall they vex us for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accepit diabolus tentandi licentiam ſed non accepit ſubruendi capiam,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> although Satan have leave to tempt us, yet he hath not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to overcome us, for there ſhall no temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> affliction take us, but ſuch as is common to man, humane and moderate, ſo indulgent is God to his children, for God is faithfull, and will not ſuffer us to be tempted or afflicted above that we are able to beare, but when the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is at the higheſt, when the affliction is at the worſt, God will make an iſſue that we may eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. The buſh that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw, burned, but was not conſumed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. The ſhip wherein Chriſt and his Diſciples were was
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:156862:16"/>covered with waves, but yet it did not ſinke, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8. And when <hi>Peter</hi> was walking upon the ſea, and ready to be drowned, then Chriſt put forth his hand and ſaved him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 14. God ſuffereth his ſervants many times to come to the very brinke of deſtruction, and then hee delivereth them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dejicit ut erigat, vulnerat ut ſanet, ut preſſura ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tur in gratiam &amp; afflictio in coronam,</hi> God hath to the us, but he will heale us, he hath ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten us, but he will binde us up againe, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6.1.</p>
            <p>I have ſeene in my experience divers of the ſervants of God, ſometimes by the violence of a fever, ſometimes by the dampe of melancholy, and ſometimes by Satans temptations brought even to the gates of hell, who have reaſoned ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eloquently and ſtrongly againſt their owne ſalvation, and that for many daies together, even to the approaching of death; (and upon perſons in the like caſe, we muſt take heed we doe not paſſe any raſh judgement, but impute their deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſpeeches unto the diſtemper of their brains, or unto the ſway of their temptations, and not unto the deſertion of grace:) And yet in the end how have they been raiſed up again, how have
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:156862:16"/>they been reſtored, according to the words of the Pſalmiſt, in the multitude of the ſorrowes which I had in my heart, thy comforts have refreſhed my ſoule, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.19. I have done with Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> petition, I come to Gods anſwer, which is my ſecond generall part. And therein I obſerved firſt Gods deniall.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had an anſwer to his Petition after many prayers, and in it a deniall; and this did not a little ſatisfie him that hee had an anſwer, though it were a deniall. For many times the long and perhaps endleſſe expectation of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is more grievous then a deniall. <hi>Et dixit mihi,</hi> and he ſaid unto me.</p>
            <p>But how God did anſwer Saint <hi>Paul</hi> here, whether immediately by himſelfe, or mediately by an Angel, whether by Viſion or Revelation, whether by lively ſpeech, or by the ſecret inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his bleſſed Spirit, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath not told us here, and therefore we muſt not bee cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to inquire.</p>
            <p>It is enough for us to know that God did an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Apoſtles, but as for the manner of the anſwer it is not for us to diſpute it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:156862:17"/>Well then the anſwer for the effect thereof was a deniall; the Apoſtle prayed often that the <hi>thorne</hi> of affliction which did ſo trouble him might be pluckt out, but it would not be; but yet he ſhall have an antidote againſt the anguiſh thereof, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A naturall man would marvell that St. <hi>Pauls</hi> complaint, being ſo lamentable, and his deſire ſo reaſonable, God ſhould deny the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate prayers of his owne ſervant, an Apoſtle, and give him a repulſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exauditur diabolus petens Iobum tentandum, &amp; non exauditur Paulus petens ſtimulum removendum,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Satan deſired leave of God to tempt <hi>Iob,</hi> and it was preſently granted him, the Apoſtle prayed often to God that the meſlenger of Satan might depart from him, and it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him, this ſeems to be a ſtrange thing: but yet neither did S. <hi>Paul</hi> diſpleaſe God with his praier, neither was God unmercifull to him in his deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; for although God did not grant St. <hi>Paul</hi> that thing which he prayed for, yet he granted him a better thing which he prayed not for; and this is Gods faſhion many times to his owne children. <hi>Non ſemper exaudit nos ad voluntate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtram, ſed ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:156862:17"/>exaudit nos ad utilitatem noſtram,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> God doth not alwaies heare us according to our wills, but he doth alwaies heare us for our good.</p>
            <p>A father denieth a knife to his young childe, becauſe he knowes he may quickly hurt himſelf therewith, and yet he denies it him in love.</p>
            <p>God is our Phyſitian, and he will not give us cold drinke when wee are ſicke of an ague, though we beg never ſo much for it. <hi>Coeleſtis medicus non facit voluntatem, ut faciat ſanitatem,</hi> our heavenly Phyſitian will not doe alwaies that which pleaſeth us, but which helpeth us. I have done with the deniall. I come now to the divine aid which God gave Saint <hi>Paul</hi> againſt the <hi>thing</hi> which did ſo trouble him, wherein the firſt thing I obſerved, is the nature and quality there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it was his Grace, <hi>Gratia mea,</hi> my Grace is ſufficient for thee.</p>
            <p>This life begins and ends in Grace, the other begins in Glory, but never ends: Grace is the preparation to Glory, and Glory is the reward of Grace, but let us ſee what Grace of God this was whereof the Lord ſpake unto the Apoſtle, for there is a twofold Grace of God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, there is <hi>Gratia Dei extra nos,</hi> the Grace of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:156862:18"/>God without us, even in God himſelfe, which is the eternall love and favour of God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he loved us and elected us in Chriſt Jeſus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternall life before the foundation of the world was laid, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. And here by the way I cannot but obſerve the ungracious dealings of the Romiſh Schoolemen with this grace of God, which is the fountain of all our happineſſe, they never diſcuſſe nor handle it at large in their diſputations, they onely name it and ſo away, we never finde them magnifying this grace of God as they ought to doe; whats the reaſon? Becauſe it makes againſt their proud doctrines of election for good workes foreſeene, and of juſtification by good workes done.</p>
            <p>Now ſome Divines underſtand the anſwer of God here of this grace of God, which if a man have, he is ſafe enough from the hurt and danger of all temptations and afflictions whatſoever: <hi>Deus meus &amp; omnia,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> give me the love and favour of my God, and I have all things: But now although this grace of God be here firſt meant, yet this grace alone is not here meant.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is <hi>Gratia dei intra nos,</hi> the grace
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:156862:18"/>of God within us, as all the gifts of Gods holy Spirit in us which are truly called Gods graces, becauſe they are the fruits and effects of that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Grace, the love and favour of God towards in Chriſt; now of this grace alſo infuſed into the ſoule of a Chriſtian man is the anſwer of God here to the Apoſtle, as that by which he was to wraſtle with, and in the end to overcome the thing that did ſo trouble him; of this grace, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, We are kept by the power of God unto ſalvation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. What power? Why the power of this grace: and from what are we kept? Why from the hurt of all temptations and afflictions whatſoever; this grace was St. <hi>Pauls</hi> token in all his Epiſtles which he writ al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with his owne hand, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p>This is the pretious jewell and ornament of the ſoul of man, and as the ſoule is the life of the body, ſo this grace is the life of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>This ſtirreth us up to all goodneſſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth us from evill; this keepes us from pride in proſperity, and from deſpaire in adverſity, this ſupports us againſt all temptations, and comforts us in all woe and diſtreſſe, this makes all our weake endeavour acceptable with God, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:156862:19"/>without this all our beſt actions are but <hi>ſplendida peccata,</hi> glittering ſins.</p>
            <p>It is not the grace of the body that can doe us any good, for it is but vanity, nor the grace of the world that can helpe us, for it is deceitfull, faith <hi>Salomon, Prov.</hi> 31.30. and in the end will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her greateſt favourites. All the grace of the world is not able to keep a man from the leaſt fit of an ague, much leſſe from a fore temptation or affliction, and when a man lyes upon his death bed, and Satan begins to tempt him, what good can all the grace of the world then do him?</p>
            <p>With this grace of God we are equall to the Angels of God in heaven; but without this grace we are worſe then Toads and Serpents, and the worſt of all Gods creatures, yea we are as bad, if not worſe then the Divells in hell: although we make never ſo faire a ſhew in the world: O then, let us pray for this grace which no chance can diſpoile us of, which no man, no creature can take from us, which never faileth us, but continueth with us for ever, Pſal. 103. For whom God loveth, hee loveth unto the end, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13. And ſo I come to the meaſure and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of this grace, <hi>ſufficit tibi, it is ſufficient for thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:156862:19"/>Sufficiency is a word of mediocrity betweene two extreames, want and abundance; for where there is ſufficient, there is neither too much nor too little.</p>
            <p>And here we may admire the wiſdome of God, who is <hi>liberimum agens,</hi> a moſt free agent, &amp; doth not worke like a naturall agent, the ſunne ſhines, the fire burnes, the water moiſtens, <hi>quoad ultimam ſphaeram activitatis,</hi> according to their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt abilities to bring forth their effects; but God giveth his grace unto every one of us accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt, as ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth beſt unto himſelfe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.7. beſtowing ſuch a proportion of Grace upon all, as is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for all.</p>
            <p>For with God is an ocean of grace, there is grace enough for you, and for me, and for us all, and for as many worlds of men as God can make.</p>
            <p>And God doth give unto every one of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants that ſufficiency of his grace whereby they ſhal be able to overcome all temptations and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and ſave their owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>Wherefore then let us not murmure againſt God, if we attaine not unto that abundance of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:156862:20"/>grace wherewith the Apoſtles, and many other Servants of God have beene endued above us; they have had the plentifull ſhowrs of Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but we will be content with the dew of his grace; they have had the full ſheaves of Gods graces, but we will bee glad of the gleanings of his grace; they have had the rich banquet of Gods graces, but we will thinke our ſelves hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, if we may have but the crummes of his grace; for if we have but ſufficiency of grace here, wee ſhall have abundance of glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>It is with Grace as it was with Manna, hee that hath much, hath nothing over, and he that hath little, hath no lacke, becauſe hee hath that which is ſufficient for him.</p>
            <p>And every grace of God that is ſufficient, is alſo effectuall, and the efficacy of grace is from it ſelf, not from the wil of man; &amp; therefore God in his anſwer here unto Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> doth not ſay, <hi>gratia mea ſufficit tecum,</hi> my grace is ſufficient with thee, but <hi>gratia mea ſufficit tibi,</hi> my grace is ſufficient for thee; for we are not ſufficient of our ſelves to thinke any thing that is good, but our ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency is of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. and therefore we muſt take heed we doe not part ſtakes between Gods
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:156862:20"/>grace and mans will, as the Papiſts doe, but wee muſt aſcribe all this ſufficiency to the grace of God, for it is he which worketh in us both to will and to do of his good pleaſure, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And therefore let us be covetous after nothing but this ſufficient grace of God, let us pray that we may have grace enough, and then we ſhall have all things enough. It is a true maxime in Divinity, there is nothing that can ſuffice the heart of man, but onely Gods grace; where ſhall you finde the man that ſaith truly and from his heart he hath enough: When he hath a houſe he ſaith, O that I had a little land to it: And when he hath that: He ſaith, O that I had a Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to it, and when he hath that, he ſaith, O that I had the Mannor that is next to it, or this Office, or that Honour, or one thing or other more; and ſtill as the world growes upon him, his deſires grow upon the world, his enough changeth alwaies, every yeare, nay every day, nay every houre he thinkes upon another enough; but let a man have grace enough, and he hath all things enough, for Gods grace is alſufficient.</p>
            <p>This ſufficient grace makes a penny ſeeme to be as big as a ſhilling, a cottage ſeem to bee as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:156862:21"/>faire as a Pallace, a priſon ſeeme to be as large as a Country, want ſeeme to be abundance, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to bee all things: This ſufficient grace makes us rich in poverty, patient in adverſity, ſtrong in weakneſſe, merry in affliction, and hopefull in deſpaire.</p>
            <p>And this grace is ſufficient for us againſt all the aſſaults of the world, the fleſh and the divell, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all troubles and afflictions whatſoever: and although God could let his ſufficient grace overcome all our temptations, all our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at firſt in a moment, yet he will not have it ſo, for God will have his graces to be exerciſed in us, <hi>tolle pugnam &amp; non erit victoria, tolle victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam &amp; non erit corona,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> if there were no conflict betweene our temptations, and Gods grace, there would be no victory, and if no victory, no price: ſometimes <hi>Amaleck,</hi> that is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and temptations prevaile, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that is grace prevaileth.</p>
            <q>Victores victique cadunt, victique reſurgunt.</q>
            <p>But in the end grace alwayes hath the upper hand, and we are more then conquerors through him that loved us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:156862:21"/>Be not then diſmaid, O thou Chriſtian ſoule, whoſoever thou art, be not diſquieted within thy ſelfe, becauſe thou art fallen into a ſore tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe thou art under an heavy affliction! what, wouldeſt thou be better then St. <hi>Paul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vide Apoſtolum patientem &amp; noli te facere deſperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> behold the Apoſtle ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and deſpaire not; nay behold Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who was tempted and afflicted, that hee might ſuccour us when we are tempted and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18. let us behold him then with a lively faith and ſure confidence, and hee will ſo ſuccour us with his ſufficient grace, <hi>Vt nec caro cum omnibus oblectamentis, nec mundus cum omnibus tormentis, nec Diabolus cum omnibus tentamentis, &amp;c.</hi> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes, that neither the fleſh with all her allurements, nor the world with all its perſecutions, nor the Divell with all his temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ſhall ever be able to ſeparate us from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now proceed to the third particular I obſerved in Gods anſwer, which is the reaſon, <hi>For my power is made perfect in weakneſſe:</hi> but I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:156862:22"/>know I have already overſpent my time, and your patience; and therefore I will leave it to the next opportunity. In the mean time let us com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend that which hath beene ſpoken unto the bleſſing of Almighty God our heavenly Father, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:156862:22"/>
            <head>The ſecond SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>The Text. <hi>2 COR. 12. and part of the ninth VERSE.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>For my power is made perfect in weakneſſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He coherence of theſe words with the former, is this, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was troubled with a ſore temptation, or ſome other affliction whatſoever it was, and he prayed often unto God that it might goe away from him: <hi>For this thing I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the Lord thrice that it might depart from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:156862:23"/>Unto this Petition God gave him an anſwer, <hi>And he ſaid unto me;</hi> and in this anſwer a loving deniall (for the Apoſtles good) of that which hee prayed for, but he gave him a better thing which he prayed not for, and that was his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly aid to make him able to encounter, and in the end to overcome the thing that did ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict him, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So farre I have already preached unto you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Text, and of that which I have delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red here, I will repeat nothing; for I love not to ſay that twice in the ſame place, and in the ſame auditory, which perhaps was not worth the hearing once.</p>
            <p>I proceed now according to my promiſe, to finiſh that which is behinde, and to handle the reaſon which God gives, why the thing muſt not depart from him which did ſo trouble him, and why he muſt wraſtle with it to maſter it: <hi>Nam virtus mea in infirmitate perficitur,</hi> for my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is made perfect in weakneſſe.</p>
            <p>And let no man doubt of the truth of this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:156862:23"/>for God himſelfe hath ſaid it with his owne mouth, as the Apoſtle tells us; and it is a truth, not of a meane or ordinary matter, but of a very high point indeed, of a famous maxime or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in Divinity, full of deep and divine myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, wherein you may behold the way which God hath alwayes taken, and doth ſtill take with men, eſpecially with his Church, and in this way of God you ſhall ſee his Wiſdome and his. Goodneſſe, both for his owne glory and mans eternall bliſſe.</p>
            <p>The Axiome here is generall, it is of power in generall, and it is of weakneſſe in generall, but of whoſe power doth the Text ſpeake? Why certainly of Gods, for mans power is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in weakneſſe, as by and by you ſhall hear, and therefore the vulgar Latin tranſlation is defective here, which leaves out the pronoune <hi>mea;</hi> and reads onely thus, <hi>Virtus in infirmitate perficitur,</hi> for power is made perfect in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whereas the Greeke Text hath the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noune alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>my power is made perfect in weakneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:156862:24"/>And of whoſe weaknes doth God here ſpeak? Why certainly of mans, and of the creatures; for there can bee no weakneſſe in God. Well then you ſee I muſt handle this power in generall, and this weakneſſe in generall. But when I come to that particular kinde of weakneſſe under which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did labour here, then I will apply that particular kinde of the power of God which is proper for the ſame, that you may ſee how Gods power was perfected in the Apoſtles weaknes.</p>
            <p>But here is a ſtrange <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, conjuncture and mixture both of contrary words and matter; here is power, and here is weakneſſe, here is Gods power, and here is mans weakneſſe, both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one ſubject; nay more, here is Gods po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer made perfect in the weakneſſe of man.</p>
            <p>Doth the Sun appeare glorious in an eclipſe? is it not rather, when he ſhineth in his ſtrength? is the beauty and majeſty of a Queene ſet forth in beggars rags, or vile rayment? is it not rather in a veſture of gold wrought about with divers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</p>
            <p>Can a candle give ſo cleare a light to all that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:156862:24"/>are in the houſe thorow a Lantern, as when it is ſet open upon a candleſticke? Doth a Diamond or other precious ſtone yeeld ſo proper and kindly a luſtre lying bare upon a tray, or ſet in a wooden ring, as it doth when it is ſet in gold, and worne in the eare, or upon the breaſt? In like manner is Gods ſtrength glorious in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? is it not rather in might? Can his power bee increaſed or diminiſhed? is not his power per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ct in it ſelfe? how then can it be perfected in the weaknes of man, or of any other creature? it is true indeed, the ſtrength of man is made perfect in might, for as the man is, ſo is his ſtrength, as the two Kings of Midian ſaid to <hi>Gideon,</hi> and that truly, <hi>Judg.</hi> 8.21. And therefore <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great before him, wiſhed for moſt valiant and puiſſant enemies to encounter with, that they might ſhew their warlike ſtrength the more againſt their enemies power, and ſo make their victories the more glorious. But now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily the power of God is made perfect in weakneſſe. How? not eſſentially, for his power is ever perfect in it ſelfe, but occaſionally, becauſe it is illuſtrated, and ſet forth in the weakneſſe of the creature, and ſo made knowne unto men, as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:156862:25"/>the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22. As they that are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly patient, are alwayes patient, but their patience is then moſt conſpicuous and illuſtrious when they are in their greateſt ſufferings. Well then, it is a familiar cuſtome with God to accompliſh his greateſt workes by the weakeſt inſtruments, and the moſt contemptible meanes, nay many times by contraries, as anon you ſhall heare.</p>
            <p>But for the further opening of this point which I obſerve upon the whole frame of my text, to wit, the conjuncture of Gods power and mans weakneſſe, both together, at one and the ſame time in the ſame ſubject, and of the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of the one in the other, you ſhall ſee it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Gods owne children almoſt thorow the whole courſe of their lives.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>When we are weake, then are we ſtrong.</l>
               <l>When we are poore, then are we rich.</l>
               <l>When we are fooles, then are we wiſe.</l>
               <l>When we are miſerable, then are we happy.</l>
               <l>When we are unknowne, then are wee vvell knowne.</l>
               <l>When we are deſpiſed, then are wee honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:156862:25"/>When we are ſimple, then are we prudent.</l>
               <l>When we are humble, then doe we boaſt.</l>
               <l>When we are beſides our ſelves, then are we ſober.</l>
               <l>When we muſt pleaſe no man, then muſt we pleaſe all men.</l>
               <l>When we muſt care for nothing, then muſt we provide all things.</l>
               <l>When we have nothing, then doe wee poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſe all things.</l>
               <l>When we are here in earth, then are wee in heaven.</l>
               <l>When we can doe nothing, then can we doe all things.</l>
               <l>When we are ſorrowfull, then do we rejoyce.</l>
               <l>When we are mortified, then are we quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</l>
               <l>When we are dead, then are we alive.</l>
               <l>When we would doe evill, then would we doe good.</l>
               <l>When we loſe our lives, then do we find them.</l>
               <l>When we are ſinners, then are we righteous.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Theſe mixtures of power and infirmity are riddles and paradoxes indeed to fleſh &amp; bloud,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:156862:26"/>to nature reaſon, and a naturall man cannot underſtand them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; but they are Evangelicall Axiomes, yea they are principles of Faith and Religion to us that are Chriſtians, and they are verified in us without any contradiction at all, as you ſhall heare.</p>
            <p>When wee are <hi>weake</hi> in body by reaſon of ſickneſſe, or any diſtreſſe, then are we <hi>ſtrong</hi> in the Lord, and in the Spirit of his might unto all patience with joyfulneſſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.11.</p>
            <p>When we are <hi>poore</hi> in ſpirit, even in the inmoſt receſſes of the ſoule to the acknowledgement of our owne unworthineſſe and wickedneſſe, then are we <hi>rich</hi> in Faith, and then doe we make many rich in Chriſt, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10.</p>
            <p>When wee are <hi>fooles</hi> in the opinion of the world, then are we wiſe in God unto ſalvation, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</p>
            <p>When we are <hi>miſerable</hi> in enduring afflictions and reproaches, then are we <hi>happy,</hi> being thereby tried and made fit for heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10.</p>
            <p>When we are <hi>unknowne</hi> to the world, then are we <hi>well knowne</hi> and opproved of God and good
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:156862:26"/>men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.18.</p>
            <p>When we are <hi>deſpiſed</hi> of wantons and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons, then are we pretious and <hi>honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> in Gods ſight, <hi>Eſay</hi> 43.4. and before his holy Angells, who rejoice at our repentance, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.10. and alſo in the eyes of all upright and juſt men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4.</p>
            <p>When we are <hi>ſimple</hi> concerning evill, then are we prudent and wiſe unto that which is good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.19.</p>
            <p>When we are <hi>humble</hi> in our ſelves before God and men, then doe we <hi>boaſt</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> in the croſſe of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14. and alſo in reproaches, in neceſſities, in perſecutions, in diſtreſſes for Chriſts ſake, in the tenth verſe of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>When we are <hi>beſides our ſelves</hi> in any heavenly extaſie or divine rapture, and contemplation of Gods goodneſſe, mercy and love to us, which Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> calls <hi>ſanam &amp; ſanctam quandam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaniam,</hi> a ſound and an holy kinde of madneſſe, which <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> had, then are we <hi>ſober</hi> in our ſelves and towards men, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13.</p>
            <p>When we muſt <hi>pleaſe no man</hi> by flattery or for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:156862:27"/>our own ends, then muſt we <hi>pleaſe all men</hi> in all things (that are good) for their edification, that they may be ſaved, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.33.</p>
            <p>VVhen we muſt be <hi>carefull for nothing</hi> inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately and immoderately, and with diſtruſt, then muſt we <hi>provide all things,</hi> honeſt in the ſight of men, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.21. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.</p>
            <p>VVhen we <hi>have nothing</hi> of this worlds upon which we ſet our hearts and deſires, then do we <hi>poſſeſſe all things</hi> in contentment, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10.</p>
            <p>VVhen we are here in <hi>earth</hi> in our perſons, then are we in <hi>heaven</hi> in our converſation, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20.</p>
            <p>VVhen we can <hi>doe nothing</hi> of our ſelves, then can wee <hi>doe all things</hi> through Chriſt that ſtrengtheneth us, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. what, all things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that can be done? No, but all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and fit for us to doe.</p>
            <p>VVhen we <hi>are ſorrowfull</hi> for our diſtreſſes, then doe we <hi>rejoyce</hi> in the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4. that is in his protection, in his favour, in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and in his ſervice; yea when ye are <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull</hi> for our ſinnes, then doe we rejoice in our repentance, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10.</p>
            <p>VVhen we are <hi>mortified</hi> in the fleſh, then are
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:156862:27"/>we <hi>quickned</hi> in our mortall bodies by the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11.13.</p>
            <p>VVhen we are <hi>dead</hi> unto ſinnes, then doe wee <hi>live</hi> unto righteouſneſſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24.</p>
            <p>VVhen we <hi>would doe evill</hi> by the ſuggeſtion of the old man, then would we <hi>doe good</hi> by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the new man, <hi>Rom</hi> 7.19.</p>
            <p>VVhen we <hi>loſe our lives</hi> for Chriſts ſake and the Goſpells here in this world, then doe <hi>we ſave</hi> them in the world to come, <hi>Marke</hi> 9.35.</p>
            <p>VVhen we are <hi>ſinners in our ſelves,</hi> then are we <hi>righteous before</hi> God in Chriſt, being juſtified freely by his grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. and having the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt imputed to us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.8. And ſo having taken a generall view of the Text, I come to a particular ſurvey thereof, <hi>My power is made perfect in weakneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The power of God is one and the ſame in it ſelfe, but it is diverſe to us, in reſpect of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall objects, and matters wherein it doth ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; and in this ſenſe, I finde three kindes of the power of God in the Scriptures, and but three</p>
            <p>Firſt, there is <hi>virtus brachii</hi> the power of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:156862:28"/>Gods arme, vvhereof vve read in the 20. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and the 6. verſe, in the 51. of <hi>Eſay,</hi> and the 9. and in the 27. of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> and the 5. and everywhere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is <hi>virtus gratiae,</hi> the power of Gods grace, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls in the verſe next after my text, the power of Chriſt: of which we reade everywhere almoſt in the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there is <hi>virtus gloriae,</hi> the power of Gods glory, or his glorious power, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.9. which ſhall be ſhewed in the world to come.</p>
            <p>But the weakneſſe of the creature, eſpecially of man, is manifold, yea of infinite variety, but I may reduce all unto theſe three ſeverall heads or ſorts; <hi>the weakneſſe of nature,</hi> the weakneſſe of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings now, and the <hi>weakneſſe</hi> of corruption, of conſumption, and as it were of annihilation af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death.</p>
            <p>Now under theſe three kindes of power ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed by God, and under theſe three heads of weakneſſe appearing in man, I will compriſe all my enſuing meditations upon this text. And I will ſhew firſt, that the power of Gods arme is made perfect in the weakneſſe of the creature in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:156862:28"/>but particularly of mans nature. Secondly, that the power of Gods grace is made perfect in the weakneſſe of mans ſufferings here in this life. Thirdly, that the power of Gods glory is made perfect in the weakneſſe of corruption, conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and annihilation, by the reſurrection of the body out of the duſt of the earth, unto life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. I begin with the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The power of Gods arme is made perfect in the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the creature in generall, and particularly of mans nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Virtus mea, &amp;c. My power is made perfect in weakneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God made man (the maſter-piece of all his Creation) not of any precious ſtone, nor of gold, or ſilver oare, nor of braſſe, or any other metall, nor of a rocke, nor of oake, or any other tree, nor of any fruit or flower, but of vile and dull earth, yea <hi>ex pulvere terrae,</hi> of the very duſt of the earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. the baſeſt and barreneſt part of the earth. Why ſo? to ſhew his power the more in mans weakneſſe, and to teach us not to glory, or to put any confidence in duſt.</p>
            <p>What miraculous things did God worke by <hi>Moſes</hi> rod, a plaine ſticke, a Shepheards ſtaffe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:156862:29"/>which hee carried in his hand the wilderneſſe to rule his ſheep with, which <hi>Moſes</hi> afterward called <hi>virgam Dei,</hi> the rod of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.20. and all this was to ſhew the power of Gods hand in the weakneſſe of a ſmall contemptible piece of Wood.</p>
            <p>When the walls of the City of Jericho fell downe flat onely with the blaſt of the trumpets of Rams hornes, and with the ſhout of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 6.20. Was not the <hi>power</hi> of Gods <hi>arme</hi> ſhewed in weakneſſe?</p>
            <p>It had been an eaſie matter for <hi>Samſon</hi> alone in his great ſtrength quickly to have killed many thouſands with a ſword in his hand; but when hee ſlew a thouſand men onely with the jaw bone of an Aſſe, which he found by chance, and all before he caſt it away out of his hand, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 15.15. Then God ſhewed indeed the <hi>ſtrength of his owne arme</hi> in weakneſſe.</p>
            <p>VVhen <hi>Elias</hi> with his mantle divided the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Jordan hither and thither, and made a dry vvalke for himſelfe and his ſervant to paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the River, 2 <hi>King</hi> 2.8. and when the bones of <hi>Elizeus</hi> raiſed a dead man unto life againe, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 13.21. (vvhoſe corpſe vvas caſt in haſt into
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:156862:29"/>the Sepulchre of the Prophet) and that as ſoone as ever the dead body did but touch the dead Prophets bones, did not God manifeſt the <hi>power</hi> of his <hi>hand</hi> in the vveakneſſe of thoſe things?</p>
            <p>God made young <hi>Daniel</hi> and his three com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions fairer and fatter in fleſh, vvith nothing but pulſe and water, then all the children of their ſort were with the daily proviſion of the Kings meat and of his wine, <hi>Dan.</hi> 1.15.</p>
            <p>The New Teſtament affords as many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of this maxime as the Old, how that God hath perfected the <hi>power</hi> of his <hi>Arme</hi> in poore inconſiderable and contemptible things: by the touchonly of the hem of Chriſts garment, all diſeaſes were perfectly cured, <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.36. nay with handkerchers that were brought from Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> body, not onely diſeaſes, but evill ſpirits departed from men, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.12. nay with the very ſhadow of <hi>Peter</hi> paſſing through the ſtreets of Jeruſalem, ſicke folke were healed, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.15. Nay more, God hath ſhewed the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of his hand in the weakneſſe not onely of contemptible, but alſo of contrary things; for Chriſt opened the eyes of one that was borne blinde with clay and ſpittle, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.6.11. enough
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:156862:30"/>to have put out his eyes if he could have ſeene well before, <hi>nam lutum &amp; ſputum quid adoculum,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here by the way I cannot but obſerve how the Papiſts abuſe and diſhonour this power of Gods hand, by transferring the honour due to God, unto the weakneſſe of the creature, by their groſſe ſuperſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion and idolatry, in the veneration and worſhip of reliques; and unto their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition in practice, they adde error in doctrine: for they teach that there is an inherent vertue in thoſe things wherein God once ſhewed the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of his hand, whereas indeed there is none at all, no more then there is in a courſe canvaſſe bag, after the gold is all powred out. And unto their errour they adde impoſture, for they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive people with counterfeit reliques: and unto their impoſture they adde filthy lucre, for the great <hi>Demetrius</hi> of Rome, and his craftſmen make great gaine by their reliques.</p>
            <p>And unto their curſed gaine they adde their temptations of Gods power, by their ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous addreſſes unto their reliques, expecting mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:156862:30"/>and cures, and helpes from them. But I leave them with their reliques, and proceed to ſhew you how God hath not onely perfected the power of his arme in the weakneſſe of the creatures below man, but alſo and eſpecially in the weakneſſe of man himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Who would ever have thought that <hi>Moſes,</hi> an infant, expoſed to deſtruction in an arke of bulruſhes, ſhould afterwards have beene the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer of all Gods people? Who would ever have imagined that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> being ſold for a bond-ſlave to ſtrange Merchants, ſhould afterwards have beene Lord over all Aegypt? VVho would ever have believed that <hi>David,</hi> the youngeſt of his fathers ſonnes, of whom little or no account at all was made, and therefore his father brought him not with the reſt of his brethren to the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but left him in the field with his ſheep: I ſay, who would ever have beleeved that hee ſhould have beene called immediately from following the Ewes great with young, and have beene an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed King over Iſrael, and have changed his ſhepheards crooke for a royall Scepter? but this was the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes. And we have ſeene by experience, that God
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:156862:31"/>hath raiſed up meane mens ſons to be very great inſtruments of his glory, both in Church and Commonwealth, according to the ſaying of <hi>David,</hi> God raiſeth the poore out of the duſt, and the needy out of the dunghill, that hee may ſet him with Princes, even with the Princes of his people, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.7.8.</p>
            <p>But the power of Gods arme was then made perfect indeed, in the weakneſſe of man, beyond all admiration, in the reſurrection of our bleſſed Saviour from the dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cumfactor mundi factus eſt in mundo,</hi> when he that made the world was made in the world, when the Potter was made of his owne clay, when he that is immenſe was ſhut up in the Virgins wombe, when the ancient of dayes was not a day old, when eternity beganne in time, when the Word was made Fleſh, an infant and could not ſpeake; when the incarnate God, God and Man in one perſon, did hunger and thirſt, and was weary, and ſlept, and wept, and was ſorrowfull, and ſuffered paines, and was crucified and dyed, and was buried; then was he <hi>Deus verè abſconditus,</hi> a hidden God indeed,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:156862:31"/>as the Prophet ſpeakes, <hi>Eſay</hi> 45.15. then was the power of his arme hidden in the weakneſſe of man.</p>
            <p>But when he roſe againe from the dead, then was he declared to be the Sonne of God with power, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. then was the power of his arme made perfect, manifeſted and openly ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed in the weakeneſſe of fleſh.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt was dead and laid in his grave, and the ſtone was ſealed, <hi>ne mors exire aut vita intrare poſsit,</hi> as <hi>Chryſologus</hi> irronically ſpeakes of the chiefe Prieſts and Phariſees, leaſt death ſhould chance to ſteal out, or life happen to creep in, the Divells thought all was cock ſure, they did even laugh to themſelves, and dance as it were upon the Sepulchre for joy, ſinging their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and triumphant ſongs, ſurely he is now ſo low, that he can never riſe againe; then, even then did he riſe againe from the dead, and perfect the power of his arme in the greateſt weakneſſe of humane nature. <hi>Gemina virtus &amp; revixit, &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dixit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſologus:</hi> here was a double power, he did not onely riſe from the dead, but he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told that he would riſe.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:156862:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:156862:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:156862:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:156862:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:156862:34"/>It was a great power for a living man to raiſe a dead body to life againe, as <hi>Peter</hi> did <hi>Dorcas, Acts</hi> 9. but it was a greater power for a dead body to raiſe up a dead body to life, as the bones of the dead Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> the dead man that was caſt in haſte, and by chance into his grave, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.7. but it was the greateſt power of all for a dead man to raiſe up himſelfe unto life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſo did Chriſt, and ſo did never any but Chriſt, neither ſhall any ever doe it againe; he onely had power to lay downe his life, and he onely had power to take it up againe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. and he roſe againe from the dead, <hi>nunquam mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus</hi> never to dye any more, death hath no more dominion over him; ſo then I may truly ſay with Saint <hi>Auſtine, Non babuit divinitas quò ſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteret humiliùs neque habuit humanitas quò ſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolleret altiùs,</hi> the Godhead could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly deſcend any lower then to take the weake nature of man, and the manhood could not poſſibly aſcend any higher, then to be united per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally unto the Sonne of God.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the power of Gods Grace which is made perfect in the weakneſſe of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:156862:34"/>mans ſufferings here in this life, which is my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond point.</p>
            <p>Which that you may the better underſtand, I will ſhew you how the <hi>power of Gods grace</hi> is made perfect in the weakneſſe of mankinde, and of the weakeſt of mankinde, and in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſufferings that the weake nature of man can beare; I will touch upon all the ſeverall kindes of weakneſſe vvherein the power of Gods grace is made perfect.</p>
            <p>And firſt this power of Gods Grace is perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the weakneſſe of mankinde; no creature under heaven is capable of Gods Grace but only man, men made of fleſh and bloud, made of duſt and ſlime, ſinfull men have this treaſure of Gods Grace in <hi>vaſis teſtaceis</hi> in earthen veſſells, that the excellency of the povver may be of God and not of men, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. We are <hi>cophini ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis coeleſtis,</hi> the baskets vvherein the ſeed of Gods word is put vvhich is able to ſave our ſoules, vve are the cabinets wherein the pretious jewells of the bleſſed Spirit of God are kept; and what ſingular lights of Grace hath God made many men in the knowledge of his ſacred Word in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:156862:35"/>vvorkes of piety and charity, and in holineſſe of life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This power of Gods Grace is made perfect in the weakneſſe of young children, for unto many of them God gave wiſdome before years, and grace before diſcretion, and the Spirit of God before the underſtanding of a man: <hi>Daniel</hi> a young youth inſpired by God, convinced and condemned to death, the two luſt-breathing El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for their falſe witneſſe againſt chaſte <hi>Suſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na;</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> a younger then he, in his little coat miniſtred before the Lord, being girded with a linnen Ephod, unto whom the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed himſelfe in a viſion, and told the young childe what he meant to doe againſt old <hi>Ely</hi> the Prieſt, for the iniquity of his houſe; but chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren younger then theſe, cried in the Temple when Chriſt came into it, <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to the ſonne of <hi>David;</hi> which when the chiefe Prieſts and Scribes heard and ſaw, they ſaid unto Chriſt in a mocking manner, heareſt thou what theſe ſay, and Jeſus replied unto them, yea, have ye never read, out of the mouthes of babes and ſucklings thou haſt perfected praiſe? <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.15.16. which words cannot be meant of babes and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:156862:35"/>ſucklings in Chriſt as many Divines would have them, for it is no wonder that they being of yeares doe praiſe God, but they are to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of babes and ſucklings in nature, as <hi>Calvin</hi> rightly expounds, and ſo they agree very well with Chriſts anſwer to the mocking Prieſts and Scribes, as if he ſhould have ſaid, it is no wonder, that little children that can ſpeake and goe up and downe doe praiſe God, when as out of the mouthes of babes and ſucklings who cannot goe nor ſpeake, God hath perfected his praiſe; but when and how this was ſo, I can better beleeve then underſtand, and more eaſily admire then expreſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the power of Gods Grace is made perfect in the weakneſſe of the weaker ſex of mankinde; you ſhall finde in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as many holy women as men, and in the New Teſtament as many women beleevers, as men; and in the Church Calenders as many women Saints and Martyrs as men, who ſhall be renowned in the Church for their faith, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and other Chriſtian vertues as long as the Goſpell ſhall be preached in the world; and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:156862:36"/>Chriſt appeared firſt after his reſurrection unto women, and by them declared his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction unto men, <hi>&amp; dum Apoſtoli dubitant, faeminae credunt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ierome:</hi> and while the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were incredulous, the women beleeved: thus hath God ſhewed the ſtrength of his Grace in their infirmity, and the power of his Spirit in the weakneſſe of their nature, that they ſhould glory not in themſelves; but in the grace of God, and in his mercy and goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the power of Gods Grace is made perfect in the weakneſſe of the loweſt conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men, in the weakneſſe of ignorance, baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and poverty; there are three things which the world admires, Wiſdome, Power &amp; Riches; all which God neglected in the calling of men to the Goſpell of Chriſt in the infancy thereof; for not many wiſemen after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble, were called at the firſt; but God choſe the fooliſh things of the world to confound the vviſe, and God choſe the weak things of the vvorld to confound the mighty, and baſe things of the vvorld, and things which are deſpiſed, did God chuſe; and things vvhich
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:156862:36"/>were not, to bring to nought things that were, that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deus ab infirmioribus incaepit;</hi> and therefore Chriſt choſe to be his Apoſtles, no diſputing Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians, no witty Poets, no eloquent Orators, no ſubtlie Mathamatitians, no deep Philoſophers, no wiſe Stateſ-man, no mighty Princes, but poore ſimple, and unlearned fiſhermen, and by them he drew whole nations of men into the net of the Church: <hi>ſcientia piſcatorum ſtultam fecit ſcientiam Philoſophorum,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> the preaching of Chriſt crucified, not by great ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, but by ignorant men, not with wit and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, but with ſimpleneſſe and plainneſſe, not pleaſing to fleſh and bloud, but contrary, to nature and reaſon; and therby to perſwade Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and Phioſophers, and the mighty men of the world, yea the very enemies and perfecutors of Chriſtian Religion, in the height of all their menacies, and moſt cruell torments, to beleive and to imbrace the Goſpell of Chriſt, and in ſo ſhort a time too, declared plainly to all the world, that the power of Gods grace was made perfect in the weakneſſe of ignoance, baſeneſſe and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:156862:37"/>And all this was done thus, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the world unto Chriſt, might not be aſcribed to the wiſdome of man, but to the power of Gods grace. But there are thoſe now, who miſunderſtanding this text, and other Scriptures of the like nature, affirme, that as ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ignorant men did heretofore without any learning or premeditation at all, preach and expound the myſteries of God, by the power of Gods Spirit, ſo ſimple and ignorant men may do the like now; and why? becauſe the power of Gods Spirit is the ſame ſtill that it was, and blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth where it liſteth, and therefore may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected as well in their weakneſſe now, as it was in the weakneſſe of others in former times; but this is no good plea, and therefore they that put the ſpirit to this now deceives themſelves, and tempt the power of Gods bleſſed Spirit, for there is a great deale of difference in the times: God gave the gifts of illumination, and of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to ſimple and ignorant men by inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on extraordinary and miraculouſly, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy of the Goſpel, and it was fit for thoſe times for the reaſon before mentioned; but now in a fetled Church ſuch miracles are ceaſed, and God
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:156862:37"/>gives divine knowledge and underſtanding un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men by labour, induſtry and ſtudy, but God doth ſtill make perfect the power of his grace in the weakneſſe of ſimple and unlearned, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing upon them the ſpirit of regeneration and ſanctification, and therfore the moſt ſimple and illiterate man alive, may beleeve as well, and as much, as the greateſt Clerk in the world: and he that weareth the linnen frock may be as holy as he that is brought up in ſcarlet, &amp; feedeth delicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and the mayd ſervant that is behind the mill, yea the beggar that imbraceth the dunghill, may bee as rich in faith and in grace, as he that ſitteth in a throne of glory.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the power of Gods grace is made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the weakneſſe of temptations: And (to apply the medicine to the malady) this was the Apoſtles caſe; God ſuffers his children to come many times in their temptations <hi>ad ripam,</hi> unto the very brinke of diſpaire, and perdition, and then the power of his grace helps them; for God is faithfull and will not ſuffer us to bee tempted above our ability; but when the temptation is at the higheſt, then he will make a way for us to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:156862:38"/>eſcape. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. God permits Satan to tempt us, and his temptations are the ſoareſt of all; but he will not ſuffer him to overcome us, <hi>latrare po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, mordere non poteſt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> Hee thinkes by his temptations to breake us, and to take us, and hold us captive at his will; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed hee takes himſelfe in his owne Gins: The more weight is laid upon an Arch, the ſtronger it is; and the winds which ſhake the trees, makes them faſter at the rootes; Satans tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions like bellowes, blow and kindle that holy fire that is within our breaſts, even the power of Gods grace: let us not then be afraid of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: For <hi>qui hortatur ut pugnemus, adjuvat aut vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambrooſe:</hi> He that incourageth us to incounter with temptations, doth and will helpe us by his grace to overcome them: <hi>Et ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebimus victoriam in eo quae nunquam victus eſt,</hi> and we ſhall be more then conquerours through him who for our ſakes was tempted and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, that we in him might overcom alſo when we are tempted: The arrowes which are often ſhot againſt a rock, are ſo blunted that afterwards they can do little or no harme at all; now Chriſt hath ſo blunted all the arrowes and darts of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:156862:38"/>temptations, by his reſiſtance, that though they hit us, yet they cannot hurt us.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, the power of Gods grace is made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the weakneſſe of our humiliation for our ſinnes: when a man is aſhamed to lift up ſo much as his eies to heaven; when a man hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles himſelfe and afflicts his ſoule with weeping and mourning for his ſinnes; when a man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies himſelfe and believes in his heart, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth that he is the greateſt ſinner in the world; when a man judgeth himſelfe not onely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the leaſt of all Gods mercies, but alſo moſt worthy of all the paines and torments in hell for offending God; when a man loathes himſelfe in his owne ſight, for the ſinnes which he hath committed; when a man abhorres him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and repents in duſt and aſhes: Yea, when a man brings himſelfe downe ſo low, that the ſhadow of death reſts upon his eye lids, and his ſpeech whiſpers out of the duſt, as it is <hi>Eſay</hi> 29.4. then doth the power of Gods grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be made perfect in him; then doth God come nigh to him to dwell with him, and to ſave him, for he that is on high will dwell with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:156862:39"/>him that is of an humble and contrite ſpirit, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the ſpirit of the humble, and to revive the ſpirit of the contrite, to heale his ſin-broken heart, and to bind up his wounds of ſorrow: <hi>Eſay</hi> 57.18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.3. And then what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation in Chriſt, what peace of conſcience, what joy in the holy Ghoſt doth the power of Gods grace preſently produce in his ſoule? which none can underſtand but hee that feeles, and none can feele but the child of God, the truely penitent ſinner; <hi>Peccator de peccato dolet, &amp; de dolore gaudet,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinner ſorroweth for his ſinnes, and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in his repentance; <hi>unam fudi lachrimam, unam inveni conſolationem,</hi> I ſhed one teare for my ſinnes, and I found thereupon one comfort; <hi>decem fudi lachrymas, decem inveni conſolationes,</hi> I ſhed ten teares for my ſinnes, I found as many comforts for the ſame, <hi>&amp; quantumcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fuit pondus lachryma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, tantus fuit numerus conſolationum,</hi> and as the weight of my teares increaſed for my ſinnes, ſo the number of Gods comforts increaſed in my ſoule according to the ſaying of the Pſalmiſt, In the multitude of the ſorrowes (even of the ſorrowes for my ſinnes) which I had in my
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:156862:39"/>heart thy comforts have rejoyced my ſoule, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.19.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the power of Gods grace is made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the weakneſſe of ſickneſſe, and of all manner of ſufferings unto which the weake na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man is ſubject; And firſt in the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſickneſſe. When <hi>Iacob</hi> was ſicke in his bed unto death, and ready to give up the Ghoſt, and when his eyes were dimme with age, that hee could not ſee, yet then did hee foreſee, and foretell what ſhould befall the twelve tribes of Iſrael in the laſt daies; what high and myſterious prophecies did he then deliver in the ſeveral bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of his twelve Sons, and with whatſtrength of words, you may reade in the 29. of <hi>Geneſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Iob</hi> was ſmitten with ſore boyls from the ſole of his foot to the crown of his head; when he ſate down among the aſhes, and ſcraped him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with a potſheard; when his skin was black and broken, and his bones were burnt with heate, when he could not ſwallow his ſpittle, and when he took his fleſh in his teeth, when the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned arrowes of the Almighty dranke up his ſpirits, and his reines were cleft aſunder; when his breath was ſtrange to his owne ſervants, nay
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:156862:40"/>to his owne wife when his ſighes were the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke to his meate, and his rorings were powred out like water; then behold the power of Gods Grace was perfected indeed in weakneſſe; then <hi>ecce Margaritae in ſterquilinio,</hi> behold what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable pearles were found upon the muck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, what an eloquent and divine Preacher <hi>Iob</hi> was upon the dunghill, what celeſtiall ſermons did he then make of Gods power, of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and of his Iuſtice? of mans miſery, the ſhortneſſe of this life, and the reſurrection after death; all as full of ſweet and heavenly conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as his body was then of loathſome ſores.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anima morbo affecta Deo propinqua;</hi> What An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall meditations, what divine raptures, what heavenly ejaculations, what ſtrong conſolation, what powerfull exhortations, what <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or full aſſurance of faith, what victories over temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, what ſwanlike ſongs, what longings to be diſſolved and to bee with Chriſt, what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracements of death have many heart-ſick and dying Chriſtians ſhewed upont heir beds and dying Chriſtians ſhewed upon their beds of languiſhing, by the power of Gods grace even to the admiration of the ſtanders by, according to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:156862:40"/>the ſaying of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 138.3. In the day when I cried unto the Lord he indued my ſoule with much ſtrength; with what ſtrength? but onely with the ſtrength of grace in his ſoule. But queſtionleſſe many of you that heare mee here this day have both ſeene theſe powers of Grace in them whom God hath brought low by ſickneſſe, and alſo have felt the like in your own ſoules when the hand of God hath beene upon you, and therefore I need not preſſe this point any further.</p>
            <p>And this power of Gods Grace is not oney made perfect in the weakneſſe of ſickneſſe, by alſo in the weakneſſe of the greateſt ſufferings of man.</p>
            <p>When my Father and my Mother forſake me, then the Lord will take me up, ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 27.10. that is, when the neereſt and deareſt friends that we liave in this world either wil not or cannot come to helpe us, when there is no man to comfort us, then doth the power of Gods Grace begin to ſhew it ſelfe in us; no diſtance of place, no cloſe priſon, no diſconſolate dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:156862:41"/>no Guard, no lockes, no iron gates can keepe the power of the bleſſed Spirit of God, the Comforter from us, but he will come in to us whereſoever we are; as he did unto <hi>Ionas</hi> in the belly of the Whale.</p>
            <p>And if God ſhew the power of his Grace in the weakneſſe of men when they ſuffer for their ſinnes, how much more will he ſhew the ſame, when they ſuffer innocently and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe; but above all when they ſuffes for Gods cauſe, and for the Goſpells ſake, as the Martyrs did, who when they heard the noiſe of whips and other inſtruments of cruelty prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for them, though they heard ſweet and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly muſicke founding in their eares, who kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and imbraced the ſtakes, whereat they were burnt, playing with the flames and trying the power thereof beforehand; as that bleſſed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Mattyr Archbiſhop <hi>Cranwer</hi> did, who burned his recanting hand in the fire, before his ſould aſcended towards heaven in the flames; who laughed bloud-thirſty Tyrants to ſcorne even to their faces, deſpiſing their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:156862:41"/>while they were more wearied in deviſing new exquiſite torments, and practiſing ſtrange kinds of deaths upon the Martyrs, then the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trys were in induring them; yea while the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors were more vexed at the patience, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, courage, faith, and joy of the Martyrs, then the Martyrs were with their tortures. And what was the reaſon of all this? why becauſe the power of Gods Grace was made perfect in their weakneſſe, <hi>Et vilis eſt omnis poena ubi virtus Dei eſt, &amp; gloriae culeſtis expectatio,</hi> and all kinds of torments, and of deaths are deſpiſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, where the power of Gods Spiritis, and the expectation of heavenly glory. And here I pray ſee the difference, betweene the ſufferings of Chriſt, and the ſufferings of the Martyrs of Chriſt; when Chriſt ſuffered, his ſoule was heavy unto death; <hi>Deus ſubtraxit protectonem ſed non diſſolvit unionem,</hi> God did not diſſolve the union of the divine and humane nature, but only with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew his protection, ſo that hee cried out upon the Croſſe, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me; which was not <hi>vox deſperantis</hi> the voice of one deſpairing, for he called him his God twice together, but <hi>vox admirantis</hi> the voice
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:156862:42"/>of one admiring that God this Father ſhould with hold all the ſweet influences of his heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſiſtance from him in his greateſt extremity, no helpe, no ayd, no ſuccour, no comfort at all then from heaven; but the humane nature of Chriſt was then left naked to it ſelfe: there was none to comfort me, ſaid <hi>David,</hi> in the perſon of Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.21. none at all, neither man nor God, neither creature nor Creator, but Chriſt as man, was left alone to himſelfe, and all this was done that our Saviour might fully ſatisfie the juſtice of God for our ſins. But contrarily now, the Martyrs of Chriſt went joyfully to their deathes, becauſe as their torments increaſed upon them, ſo the power of Gods grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaſed in them; and the more their ſufferings did abound the more did Gods comforts ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abound in them. But if Almighty God had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne the beames of his gratious aſſiſtance from them, but a little while, yea if God had but turned away his face from them, but a moment, they would not only have been troubled, as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh, but they would have trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and their knees would have ſmitten one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, at the ſight of an officers hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bart,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:156862:42"/>bart, and at the apprehenſion of death they would have ſunke downe preſently into the very gulfe of deſpaire.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the third conſideration of his power, which is the power of Gods glory; and this glorious power of God is made perfect in the weaknes of corruption, conſumption, and as it were annihilation of bodies by the reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the creatures generally; for the creature it ſelfe ſhall be delivered from the bondage of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God, <hi>Rom</hi> 8.21. but eſpecially the glorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our bodies at the laſt day accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the working of Gods power, whereby he is able to ſubdue all things to himſelfe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. And in this weak, baſe, and ignominious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of our bodies after death ſhall the power of Gods glory be made perfect; yea though our bodies make ſuch a ſtrange and long Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage thorow corruption unto nothing, as S. <hi>Cyrill</hi> ſpeakes of; though they bee devoured of fiſhes, and thoſe fiſhes be eaten up of men, and thoſe men be turned into duſt, and that duſt be ſcattered by the foure winds, yet god can picke
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:156862:43"/>up all our parts againe, and give every one his owne body: <hi>redhibentibus ea ignibus, &amp; undis &amp; alxis ferarum &amp; lactibus piſcium &amp; ipſorum temporum propria gula,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeakes: the fire, the ſea, the bellies of wild beaſts, the gutts of fiſhes, and times all-devouring throate it ſelfe ſhall yield up their dead againe: And doe not aske how this can be done; for this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>how,</hi> in the workes of God is an argument of increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as <hi>Iuſtine Martyr</hi> ſpeakes; <hi>conſidera authorem, &amp; tolle dubitationem,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> conſider the glorious power of God, and this takes away all doubting.</p>
            <p>And this glorious power of God ſhall be ſo perfected in the ignominious weake and baſe eſtate of the body after death, that it ſhall raiſe up the ſame numericall and individuall bodies unto life againe according to the Scriptures. I mervaile then that <hi>Durand</hi> the Schoolman upon the 4. of the ſentences, the 43. and 44. diſtinctions ſhould deny this numerical identity of the body in the reſurrection with this bold and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory concluſion, <hi>ſalva reverentis omnipotentia divinae dico hoc fieri non poſſe;</hi> with reverence be it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:156862:43"/>ſpoken to Gods omnipotency, this cannot bee done, ſayth hee; wherein hee ſhewed not onely hereſie, but alſo blaſphemy, and for both he is condemned by the Schooles; yea by the word of God: for all thoſe pronounes in the 19. Chap. of <hi>Iob</hi> and the 26. and 27. verſes, <hi>ego ipſe &amp; non alius ut mea,</hi> are pronounes of nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall identity; although the wormes deſtroy this body yet in <hi>my</hi> fleſh <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſee God, whom <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſee for <hi>my ſelfe,</hi> and theſe <hi>mine</hi> cies ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him, and not another. Againe Chriſt ſhall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>change</hi> our vile bodies ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. now a change is not in the ſubſtance, but in the qualities, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith <hi>Amphilochius,</hi> the body at the reſurrection ſhall be the ſame ſtill for ſubſtance, but not the ſame for qualities; <hi>nam gloriae eſt, non tollere, ſed extollere, non interfice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſed perficere naturam,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gerſon:</hi> this power of glory ſhall not deſtroy, but perfect nature in the reſurrection; <hi>alius ero, non aliud,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> I ſhall be another manner of man then, but not another thing, and Chriſt ſhall make our vile bodies like unto his glorious body, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Theodoreo, like</hi> in the quality of glory, but not equall in the quantity of Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:156862:44"/>Moreover that is called a reſurrection indeed, <hi>ubi reſurgit quod cecidit,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Ierome,</hi> where that very numericall body doth riſe againe unto life which died, as Chriſt did, and his reſurrection is the pattern of ours. And <hi>Tertullian</hi> gives the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hereof, <hi>ut integru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fiat hominis judicium,</hi> that the ſame fleſh which hath been a companion with the ſoule in vertue or vice, in holineſſe or wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe in this world, may be a companion with the ſoule either in bliſſe or in paine in the world to come, otherwiſe one body ſhould ſinne, and other body ſhould be tormented, one body ſhould ſhed its bloud for Chriſt, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther body ſhould be glorified with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But after what manner ſhall this glorious power of God be made perfect in the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our vile bodies? Why in the foure ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall qualities of a glorified body, impaſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, clarity, agility and ſpirituality, which <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> calls <hi>indumenta Angelica,</hi> Angelicall ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and <hi>Ruffinus, prerogativas carnis;</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives of the fleſh, and the Schoolemen, <hi>dotes corporis glorioſi,</hi> the indowments of a glorified body: All which foure Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:156862:44"/>ſets downe particularly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. It is ſown in corruption, it is raiſed in incorruption, there is the impaſſibility of a glorified body, nothing can hurt it, it can ſuffer nothing: it is ſowne in diſhonour, it is raiſed in honour; there is the clarity of a glorified body ſhining as bright as the Sunne in his ſtrength; it is ſowne in weakneſſe, it is raiſed in power, there is the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gility of a glorified body, as ſwift as the minde, for where the ſoule would have the body to be, there ſhall the body preſently be; it is ſown a naturall body, it is raiſed a ſpirituall body; there is the ſpirituality of a glorified body, not that it ſhall be changed into a Spirit, but that it ſhall be conformed to the Spirit, it ſhall need no food or ſleep to refreſh it; <hi>ſed quaſi in Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licum habitum commutabitur,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks, but it ſhall be as it were changed into an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall ſtate and condition in all things.</p>
            <p>Now upon this glorious power of God we build our faith and the hope of our reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of the weakneſſe of corruption unto life eternall: <hi>Sepulchrum eſt uterus reſurrectionis,</hi> the grave is the wombe of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:156862:45"/>Can a man goe into his mothers wombe and be borne againe, ſaid <hi>Nicodemus?</hi> Yes that he may, for he ſhall goe into the wombe of the earth, the mother of us all, and be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine immortall at the laſt day: <hi>Et quanto cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora noſtra nunc viliora tanto futura glorioſiora,</hi> and the more weake and vile our bodies are now, the more glorious ſhall they be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: And this duſt of ours ſhall one day bee <hi>pulvis glorificatus,</hi> glorified duſt, and duſt ſhall ariſe never to returne to duſt any more, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge <hi>8.</hi> in Tit. for firſt read firſt. pag. <hi>10.</hi> line <hi>21.</hi> Euſtocni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. p. <hi>13.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> redundantia. p. <hi>17.</hi> l. <hi>23.</hi> ſinnes. ibid. l. <hi>21.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. <hi>24.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> court like. p. <hi>25.</hi> l. <hi>13.</hi> copiam. p. <hi>27.</hi> l <hi>5.</hi> come. p. <hi>30.</hi> l. <hi>15.</hi> juſtification. p. <hi>31.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> [us] is omitted. p. <hi>57.</hi> l. <hi>11.</hi> ironically. p. <hi>63.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi> ſubtile. ib. Mathematicians. ibid. l. <hi>7.</hi> Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. ibid. l. <hi>17.</hi> Philoſophers. ibid. l. <hi>20.</hi> menaces. p. <hi>66.</hi> l. <hi>15.</hi> Ambroſe. ibid. l. <hi>18.</hi> qui. p. <hi>71.</hi> l. <hi>12.</hi> onely.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
